Guide to the Josephine Baker Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Josephine Baker Collection
1929-1968
JWJ MSS 108
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.5
(12 boxes)
Baker, Josephine, 1906-1975
Scope and Contents
The Josephine Baker Collection is comprised of correspondence, photographs, personal papers, and printed material documenting the life and career of Josephine Baker between 1929 and 1968.
Evidence of Baker's career as a performer can be found in her correspondence with managers and producers, clippings from her performances, and pamphlets and brochures from concerts. There is correspondence and printed material regarding her appearances in Argentina in 1947 and 1952 and in Canada in 1960. The collection also includes material relating to Baker's involvement in the French Resistance during the second World War as seen in a decree for the Medal of the Resistance.
Correspondence with family members, financial records, and other documents provide insight into Baker's personal life, including her financial affairs and her home in France, Château des Milandes.
Josephine Baker (1906-1975)
Josephine Baker (1906-1975), African-American dancer, singer, actress, and civil rights activist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Carol Lipton on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial Fund, and James Weldon Johnson Memorial Collection of Negro Arts & Letters Fund, 1995.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
African American civil rights workers; African American entertainers -- 20th Century; Dancers -- United States -- Archives; Singers -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Underground movements -- France; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographic prints -- United States -- 20th Century; Dancers -- France -- 20th Century; Dancers -- United States -- 20th Century; Singers -- France -- 20th Century; Singers -- United States -- 20th Century; Baker, Josephine, 1906-1975; Carol Lipton
- Notebook I, 1940-1960; 5 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Contains Baker's outgoing letters addressed to family and friends (including Christine Scotto and Jo Bouillon). Topics include Château des Milandes.
- Notebook II, 1962-1968; 8 (Box 2)
  Contains accounts relating to Château des Milandes, a typed document concerning "Mes raisons et conditionnes pour laisser ma place aux Milandes a Jo Bouillon (car j'y suis force)," notes for a press conference regarding Château des Milandes in Cologne, notes for a radio program, notes and correspondence regarding the U.S. government's refusal to renew her visa, and a note paraphrasing a letter from John F. Kennedy. The notebook also includes a letter from Jacques de Visme (March 29, 1968).
- Notebook III, 1965-1968; 3 (Box 3)
  Contains copies of Baker's outgoing letters relating to her career as well as correspondence from and concerning her children.
- Notebook IV, 1929-1967; 5 (Box 4)
  Contains correspondence, photographs, artwork, documents and printed material. Correspondence includes a note from Hadj Thami el Glaoui and congratulatory letters from Mistinguett, Jacques Soustelle, Maurice Escande, and others. Photographs spanning Baker's career can also be found in the notebook in addition to original artwork relating to "Baker Mask/Baker Buste" products. Documents consist of a contract from Lloyd's insurance (1930), contract from the Ministère du Travail (1934), decree for Médaille de la Résistance (October 8, 1946), and Insigne des commandos d'Afrique (March 16, 1945). Printed material is comprised of brochures, pamphlets, and handbills, such as a brochure about Peron dedicated to Baker, brochures about Château des Milandes, and material relating to Baker's career.
- Notebook V, 1946-1953; 6 (Box 5)
  Contains letters and documents. Correspondence includes letters with Vienna sponsors concerning performances, a letter from Marcel Achille, several telegrams dating from 1946 to 1967, and copies of outgoing correspondence. Documents include bills and other material relating to Château des Milandes.
- Notebook VI, 1934-1963; 4 (Box 6)
  Contains contracts with performers (including Pepito Abatino), correspondence with French and American managers (Larry Potter, E. Herzog, H. Margot, and Ben Waller), and letters and documents relating to Baker's financial affairs with I.M.E.F. Bank.
- Notebook VII, 1947-1952; 7 (Box 7)
  Contains a press book (1952) and printed material about Baker, including newspaper clippings and a copy of Ebony Magazine (May 1951) featuring Baker on the cover.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Also stored in: Oversize box 13
- Notebook VIII, 1952-1952; 4 (Box 8)
  Contains a press book with clippings dating from November 20 to December 11, 1952.
- Notebook IX, 1952-1960; 4 (Box 9)
  Contains a press book covering the end of Baker's tour in Argentina (1952) and arrest in Canada (1960).
- Notebook X, 1947; 5 (Box 10)
  Contains a press book and financial records for Baker's tour in Argentina.
- Notebook XI, 1947; 4 (Box 11)
  Contains a contract and financial records pertaining to Baker's tour in Argentina.
- Oversize, 2 (Box 12)
  Contains a copy of Ebony (May 1951) and a certificate awarding Baker the Brotherhood Award (1960).